Rachel Liu: Loud.
Rachel Liu: Amazing. It's recording. Thank you so much.
Joe Mo: All right.
Joe Mo: And I know Julane's gonna… has difficulty with, the.
Rachel Liu: I heard her audio, actually, very briefly.
Joe Mo: Okay.
Julane Lowe: Can you hear my audio?
Rachel Liu: Yeah, I can, I can.
Julane Lowe: Okay, perfect, so at least I can talk. Okay, great, thank you.
Joe Mo: So yeah, based on, you know, kind of the knowledge you have and the work you've clearly done, I'll stay focused on that item in terms of, you know, how can… how can the city
Joe Mo: How can you make the city better for folks, right? And how can 311 be a part of that, if you stay with that? The sense we have, and as I said, other pressure points I've raised as well, is making 311 more available and utilized by more people, as simple, you know, kind of simple wording in that respect.
Joe Mo: I'll take a moment to say we believe 311 absolutely can make the city better, right? That's kind of our starting point.
Joe Mo: As I said, the most common thing people think about when it comes to throwing one is filing a complaint, right? They call it a complaint hotline, or, you know, you submit a complaint, it's a noisy neighbor, it's a barking dog, it's a street light that's out.
Joe Mo: And all of those are important, and the city does have a vehicle to address those, so they improve quality of life, they can address infrastructure gaps, and many other things.
Joe Mo: So, it's a great mechanism in that respect, and over the years, I think it's been honed pretty well. We would still like to have it more customer-oriented than government-oriented, when you have to fill out a form, or when you want to make a request.
Joe Mo: We're getting there. We've enhanced our mobile app to have an AI element to it, where you can just take a picture and it can figure out what service requests, so you don't have to figure it out. So we're keen on doing that, but as a mechanism, we think it's very good in that respect.
Joe Mo: But I did mention that service requests are really only about 10% of all the contacts that come into 311.
Joe Mo: So, the reality is we're really an information services business, if you will, more so than a complaint hotline. We handle about 37 million customer contacts a year.
Joe Mo: They can be very, you know, surface and surface-oriented only, and
Joe Mo: and transactional, right? Someone calls 311 and wants to hear that there's an ultimate side parking status in effect or not in effect today, right? Very low engagement, but literally tens of thousands of people on a given day may call for that. And then it's much more, right? We connect people with, you know.
Joe Mo: human resources, which you mentioned before, financial assistance, food… find a food pantry. There's a whole slew of things that span health and human services, you know, infrastructure that I mentioned before,
Joe Mo: Appointments, resources that folks may not be aware of, all of that you can get by contacting 311.
Joe Mo: And when I say contacting, it's most commonly thought of as calling.
Joe Mo: But in reality, more people, engage with us on a self-serve basis than actually call. They use our website, and they use our mobile app.
Joe Mo: And even when they do call, a lot of them will just take the automated announcements that we play, and that satisfies their need. So… so it is a bigger… it's a big piece. The thing that people tend to look at in terms of engagement.
Joe Mo: is geography, right? Who's… who's contacting us and who's not? And that's in part because the most
Joe Mo: robust data that we have is the service request data, and it does have location information. We get a lot of calls for people, right, who are looking for a food pantry, right? That data doesn't exist, so you can't map… Sorry, the location data doesn't exist on that.
Joe Mo: So, you know, you can't necessarily map that and try to figure out, oh, you know, here's some areas where maybe there needs to be more food pantries, right, in a very simplistic way. So, we are a little bit, you know, trapped in the fact that the most useful, the most robust data,
Joe Mo: is really focused on complaints. It's still very useful, and it's still very robust, as it's 3.5 million,
Joe Mo: records 3.5 million complaints a year, just by way of comparison, you know, the city of Chicago is probably the second largest 311 in the country, and they handle about 3.5 million contacts a year, right? So we're, like, order of magnitude 10 times larger than Chicago and Philly and San Fran, and even LA.
Joe Mo: So it's good in that respect. Now, getting down to that, using that as the assumption that that's the best data set to kind of look at who's contacting 311 and who's not.
Joe Mo: There's lots of ways to look at it, but it generally comes back the same way, right?
Joe Mo: you know, you can index by… by neighborhood, by zip code, right? You can index by, financial strata, right? Whether someone's in a, you know, high, medium, low affordability area. You can do all that sort of cutting with the data.
Joe Mo: But what you're left with is, is 311… is… are there underserved communities? And if so, why? And are those underserved… and so let me stay, go back to that. Are there underserved communities, and if so, why, right?
Joe Mo: If there are, then…
Joe Mo: And the assumption is 311 is a good thing for communities, then we need to find a way to get into those communities and make them aware of 311, or more likely, instill some trust in contacting the government.
Joe Mo: I would say over the years, 20-plus years that 301's been around, it's not… it's unlikely that people are not aware of 301 on a broad scale, right? They may not know what it is, it may not be relevant to them, but the concept or the number is likely not lacking for awareness. Our…
Joe Mo: non-empirical experience is that some communities just don't trust calling the government. Not necessarily three-on-one, but just contacting the government. And therefore, how do you address that? We've tried to address that by instilling and over-focusing on
Joe Mo: the privacy aspect, that you can trust calling 311. We're not collecting your information unless it's needed for a specific complaint type, but otherwise.
Joe Mo: we don't know and don't care, in a way, right, who you are when you're calling. Our goal is to give you the answer. And I often cite, you know, very personal situations. We have people who are calling for
Joe Mo: help with mental health. We have people calling about, you know, questions about neonatal care or abortion services, right? Those are very private, very personal conversations. So.
Joe Mo: We see it as somewhat of a metric that as long as people contact us about those things, then our commitment to trust and privacy is holding up, right?
Joe Mo: But I suspect, you know, that's part of the underserved universe as well, it's just not the quantified universe, so… But yeah, that's a lot of talking on my part. I'll… let me bring that to a close and say I think that's the biggest opportunity, again.
Joe Mo: crack the code on, is there underserved… are there underserved communities? If so, why? And then what can we go do with that?
Joe Mo: I'll stop. I'm good.
Rachel Liu: Yeah, that's super helpful. So I guess, like, to repeat what you've shared back to you,
Rachel Liu: it seems like there's a big effort this year, especially, or within this administration, to, really focus on outreach and making sure that people are using this resource that's provided for residents. Besides privacy and improving on, like, just making sure people know that their information is kept private, what other, like, outreach
Rachel Liu: kind of initiatives are being done to… to address this concern. And, and…
Rachel Liu: Like, are you measuring success by, like.
Rachel Liu: I guess, how are you measuring success? Like, if this outreach initiative is working?
Joe Mo: So, great question, and the short answer is there is not an outreach effort, right?
Rachel Liu: Oh, I see, I see.
Joe Mo: Yeah, it's the… literally the last kind of public one in terms of traditional mode, right, of advertising, you know, doing something in the community.
Joe Mo: goes back over 10 years. It's a function of 311 itself doesn't have an advertising budget. The city relies on, essentially, the mayor's, you know, pulpit as the message.
Joe Mo: But there's not really an outreach effort. We will periodically… in the past, we periodically worked with certain elected officials in certain areas, but even that is very limited, right? It may be providing flyers, you know, for a table event that a community board or a council district's gonna have.
Joe Mo: It's not really been a concentrated effort.
Joe Mo: I mentioned that our plan for the next year starts off with getting into that on a more formal basis.
Joe Mo: I'll put it kind of frankly. In the past, because, you know, there's 51 council districts in New York City, there's another set of elected official or semi-elected officials called community boards.
Joe Mo: Periodically, many have asked us to kind of come and speak at their events.
Joe Mo: we've not been able to do that simply because of resources, right? We could do it for one, but we can't do it for 50 on a regular basis. So, now we're looking to toss that model out, and Julane is going to have a very, very small team of one person, who's going to help us kind of pick and choose, or target
Joe Mo: Where we think we need to be, based on
Joe Mo: elements of underserved, or even just what we know, right? A vulnerable community. I think everyone hesitates to say it this way, but I'll say it, you know, no one's overly worried to going… that… are we serving or underserving a, let's call it a wealthy community?
Joe Mo: there is concern if you're serving a predominantly, you know, poorer community, and if you've got to put efforts into outreach, go there, as opposed to going to the other one. That could be wrong on many levels, but fundamentally, I think that's the thought process, right?
Joe Mo: who's not contacting us, and then, again, figuring out why not, and then how do we address that. But the why not is really a key, because you can't solve unless you know why.
Rachel Liu: Yeah, that's a really interesting problem to have, because you're kind of stuck between wanting to keep people's information private, so you don't want to collect very much information, but then you don't know, like, who needs the most help in the city. Yeah, that does make sense.
Joe Mo: We do a lot of… over the years, we've done what we'll call qualitative, you know, and one of our best sources for how is 311 working is definitely not quantitative, through surveys or counts. It's through our own staff, right? So, a call taker, a call center representative, that's the term we use.
Joe Mo: talks to 10,000 New Yorkers a year, right? So, multiply that by 100-plus call takers, we've got a pretty good focus group, if you think of it that way.
Rachel Liu: Got it.
Joe Mo: on, you know, first year of being here, they're just learning how to do the job, but after a few years, they're very valuable in terms of, this makes sense, this doesn't make sense, I never hear from people from this area, I hear from people from that area. So you can't use the data, but for us, it's a touchstone more than anything else.
Rachel Liu: Is there a formal focus group?
Rachel Liu: that meets, like, with all the people from the cost… from the call centers. They seem like a very valuable asset to…
Joe Mo: There's not a formal one. I've tried for several years to sell it as a product that we could charge money for, but that doesn't work in government services, so… No, it's more ad hoc. We've had some folks come in and do, you know, kind of roundtables with agents just to get a perspective.
Joe Mo: And we also push the mayor's office often to say, if you tell us in advance an idea, we can give you pretty good customer feedback on whether customers are going to like it or not. So, but nothing formal, unfortunately.
Rachel Liu: Got it, got it.
Rachel Liu: And then, I have another… oh wait, let me let Mujaba go first. Yeah. Mujaba, do you have any questions?
Mujtaba Asghar: Yeah, yeah, I've been, I've been listening to the conversation, by Joe. So…
Mujtaba Asghar: I, from what I understand, there's major factions, and you're dealing with something with very delicate issues also, and you're maintaining privacy. But, is there any effort by, 311 or the Office of Technology and Information at NYC, this department, to preempt the needs of the residents?
Mujtaba Asghar: Which means that,
Mujtaba Asghar: for now, you, the department knows that, okay, this resident needs this particular help in, like, in their lifestyle, only if they make an active effort to reach you guys out. However, is there any effort being done
Mujtaba Asghar: To profile the residents, or to make sure that the city administration learns the residents before they raise the concern, and before, like.
Mujtaba Asghar: My specific question, revolves around how can… revolves around how might we question that we have in front of us, which means the city needs to learn. So, is there any effort, being done right now around that?
Joe Mo: It's a great question, and very insightful. I'll say the short answer is no, and then I'll explain why. In part, we do…
Joe Mo: have a sense of that, right? We know the… maybe not at the customer level, but we know people are gonna call about certain things, right? And…
Mujtaba Asghar: Okay.
Joe Mo: we… the majority of people who call 311 every year are, you know, one or two times a year. They're not necessarily frequent. But there are many who are frequent, right? Or there are many who are calling about the same thing, so we can…
Joe Mo: predict what's going to happen based on history. For example, every May, the city promotes a heating assistance plan.
Joe Mo: Which essentially is, you can submit a request through 311 to go to the Human Resources Department, who you met with last week, for low-cost or free air conditioners, right?
Joe Mo: Which is a godsend for people who don't have one, especially elderly or vulnerable folks from a health perspective. So we know, you know, about the time when it's gonna get announced, we know when the enrollment's gonna be, we also know when the enrollment's gonna be done.
Joe Mo: But every year, we let that volume come into us, instead of proactively going out and giving the folks who need it a heads up.
Joe Mo: And in part, it's just the mechanism of how we work, right? We're intake, not output, not outreach. But it also goes back to that privacy factor, right? If you contact us, we don't want to be calling you back.
Joe Mo: like we're stalking you. Or, hey, you've called 5 times for an air conditioner every year, just want to give you the heads up it's coming this year. It would actually be a great service if we did that, but the process and the safeguards don't necessarily allow for that.
Joe Mo: The best I can say we do is we've offered… you could sign up for an account, on 311 Online.
Joe Mo: A relatively small number, thousands, tens of thousands maybe have signed up for an account, and most don't actually engage with it. But that would be one way… that's one way we envisioned, hey, if you did that, now we've got your permission, you've opted in, we could engage with you more, right?
Joe Mo: The challenge there, we find that people only engage with 311 once or twice a year on items that are not necessarily predictable to them or us. So that hasn't really worked well.
Joe Mo: And then, you know, during an emergency, we'll push notifications out, but that's not necessarily what you're getting at. So, we believe that you could do that.
Joe Mo: But we've not pushed it because we've… we've leaned more towards the over, kind of, overemphasized privacy and trust versus, you know, proactive outreach.
Mujtaba Asghar: Okay, perfect. One follow-up question on this. I heard, with your conversation with Rachel that the department does not have a marketing budget, so you do not have an advertising budget.
Mujtaba Asghar: Is this… is this, an institutional thing, or is there, like, you… like, the department is facing a budget cut or something? Is this not part of the process? Like, I'm gonna understand it over here.
Joe Mo: Okay. Yeah, it's more not part of the process than necessarily a budget cut. Even in years when we weren't facing budget cuts, there was really no marketing. When 3011 first launched 23 years ago, the marketing effort was to slap bumper stickers on taxi cabs, because
Joe Mo: That was the best free advertising you could get, and unlike today, there were, you know, 10 times more yellow taxis in the city, so it actually was a pretty effective marketing campaign.
Joe Mo: But the approach has been, you know, let the mayor announce it and, you know, promote it through press releases and try to work with community boards. It's a little bit of a challenge because council districts and community boards want 311 to do things, but they also want their constituents to come to them
Joe Mo: As opposed to going to 311. So, it's a little bit of a double-edged sword there. The council members get upset if someone says, 311 told me to call you.
Joe Mo: But at the same time, they want constituents to go through their office first, right? So we've got to work on that to kind of be more shared in our focus, and that… I think that stems from the lack of
Joe Mo: concerted outreach or partnership, because of resources over the years. So there's a few examples there, but fundamentally, it's not in our budget. It's not even… it's not even something the city looks at in terms of its budget. And if there is promotion of 311, it's because
Joe Mo: the mayor came to the call center and took 3 calls on March 11th, which is our 311 day, and, you know, got a kabilion likes. So, that's kind of the extent of our promotion.
Mujtaba Asghar: Okay, perfect, perfect. I think, these were the two questions from my side, Rachel.
Rachel Liu: Okay, perfect.
Joe Mo: I realize that I've kind of run long here on a few things, but we're okay if we want to go longer than 11.30, if that works for you, so…
Rachel Liu: Yeah, I've got… yeah, yeah, that works for me. I have…
Rachel Liu: honestly, a billion follow-up questions, but let me just do it based off priority. So, I know, something we've heard from other conversations we had is kind of this thing that you briefly touched on, which is this lack of, like.
Rachel Liu: concerted outreach, like, just, of… of different organizational or, like, government bodies working together to address, like, a specific issue. We've heard comments from,
Rachel Liu: specifically, like, the Civic Engagement Board saying how sometimes frustrated residents would CC, like, every single person on their board to try and get a response. And there isn't, like, currently, from what I've heard, a way of
Rachel Liu: like, figuring out exactly what agency should represent or should deal with, like, the problem at hand, just because there's, like, different ownership and everything. Is this a problem that you guys face in, like, your own sense, or do you think this is kind of, like, not really something that needs to be addressed?
Joe Mo: I think it's something that can be addressed, or… and should be addressed. It's…
Joe Mo: It's not… when I take a step back and think of, you know, 37 million customer contacts a year, it's not the biggest thing by any means. It tends to be smaller, but we're handling the macro well, so it is something that's worth going and looking at at the micro side.
Joe Mo: And the themes, the examples you mentioned kind of fit the themes over the years, right? It doesn't work for me for this reason, or it didn't do this for me, or I wasn't aware I could do this with 311. So, so yeah, we…
Joe Mo: don't want to rule anything out in terms of an opportunity to find a way to do better outreach.
Joe Mo: But then we lack some of the vehicles to go do so.
Rachel Liu: Yeah, no, fair, fair. And then… and then on the outreach side, maybe this is more of just, like, a, like, throwing it out there, but have you, have you, like, used or worked with the people who have made, like, reported NYC or CClickFix, which I believe are, like, both…
Rachel Liu: mobile apps, that are maybe to… to address, kind of, issues like this for, for deep, for, like, not…
Rachel Liu: For, like, low usage, potentially, of 311.
Joe Mo: I'm familiar with both of them, in particular C-ClickFix. I will say the answer to that is we have not, and going back years, I would say that was by design.
Joe Mo: I won't… I wouldn't call it competitors, right? But there was very much a schism between working with the C-Click Fixes of the world, and large part just because it's the city mentality sometimes, right? They're not authorized, we are, we can't work in this space, and they can. So, there were kind of walls
Joe Mo: You know, arbitrary walls that were built, but there was never really any work, with that.
Joe Mo: What I will say, though, the flip to that is we do…
Joe Mo: we have partnered, I always say over the years, right? So I'm dating myself, but… but we have partnered with other 311s around the country. We have very good relationships with a lot of cities, large and small. Julane is our representative onto an executive… a national executive committee of 311s, so there's… there is exchange of, hey, what works for you and what works for us, and vice versa.
Joe Mo: I will say the, kind of, the question of who's served and who's underserved, exists in just about every 311 in the country, for all the same reasons, right? We know a lot about who contacts us.
Joe Mo: we don't know a lot about those who don't contact us, including why. And most 311s are similar in that they don't really have an outreach.
Joe Mo: budget, whether it's marketing, whether it's staff, or anything to that effect. So there's really not a lot to gain there, but a little bit of a long-winded answer to your question, but when it comes to the CClick fixers and the other folks, and the… I think Live 3-on-1 is a new one that we met with recently, yeah, there's no relationship there.
Rachel Liu: Got it. Okay, that's super helpful. I know we are out of time. I have one more follow-up question, also kind of in the same vein, but have…
Rachel Liu: You guys thought about… because I guess I'm thinking about, like, transit, right? Transit is kind of like the ways of, like, a public transit city is kind of
Rachel Liu: how I see it, where it kind of becomes, like, a social media experience to get people to engage, rather than just, like, only use it to report certain complaints that they have. Is this something that has, like, crossed…
Rachel Liu: the mind of the developers of the 3-on-1 app, of, like, potentially increasing service, or… Increasing usage?
Joe Mo: I follow what you're describing, and I think that's a terrific idea. We've really not, done that, and
Joe Mo: again, we're probably too inward-focused, right? When we invest time in the mobile app, it's to, you know, add more features or, you know, some enhancements that we can do. We've not looked to overhaul the mobile app, for example.
Rachel Liu: Got it.
Joe Mo: just the… as you just described, what you just said, as you were describing, I thought, wow, that's a pretty cool idea. And we've not done that.
Rachel Liu: Okay, yeah, and then, and I guess, sorry, another follow-up to that is, like, if we work… because by the end of this, we're expected to have, like, a working app. I mean, we're technologists, so we are going to be building something at the end of it.
Rachel Liu: What would the process be like if, you know, let's say we do this, we do focus groups, it turns out, like, people are really engaging with this? What would the process be like to either integrate this into, kind of, the existing government tech stack, or, you know, like, go through that process?
Joe Mo: Hmm, that's a great question, and I'll give you an answer, and then if you proceed through, I can connect you with folks on our team who could do more. But the short answer is, we don't connect with you, but you can have access to us through the API.
Rachel Liu: Okay, got it.
Joe Mo: And just so you know, we don't connect with you, because if we did it for one, we'd have to do it for all, right? I see. And usually someone's doing an app, developing an app, for a, you know, parochial reason, and then government can't be…
Joe Mo: You know, partnering with one without a formal contract and all that good stuff, but…
Rachel Liu: Right, right.
Joe Mo: We've done a lot of trials with AI vendors, from everything from the mobile app. We've even done a voice, a phone call AI situation. We did a pilot. We ended up doing it twice.
Joe Mo: But did a lot of demos, and those vendors were able to kind of use our API to be able to connect.
Joe Mo: I would, you know, I would get people who can explain that better than I can, but if it's something you want to pursue, we'd be happy to support that.
Rachel Liu: It's something we would absolutely love to pursue. So yeah, if you could connect us, that would be amazing, and we're 5 minutes or 3 minutes over,
Joe Mo: Okay, sorry.
Rachel Liu: much for… I don't know, Julane, do you have anything to add? Mujtaba, do you have anything to add?
Mujtaba Asghar: I think most of the things are covered. You asked the question regarding the tech stack, that was revolving in my… in my head. I think that's about it from my side. Thank you so much, Joe.
Julane Lowe: Yeah, I'm sorry, guys, I wasn't able to participate a little bit more, but nobody knows this stuff better than Joe, so he is all 311, so if anything else does come up, you can reach out to us.
Joe Mo: Yeah.
Joe Mo: I'll also add, we're interested in what you come up with. As I said, we've always been that way, but this year, I feel good that
Joe Mo: this administration, this mayor, this time is our chance to really do what we wanted to do in the past, you know, 20 years, and not been able to. And getting input, we… I'll be very frank, Julane came here… gosh, Julane, 6 years ago now?
Joe Mo: Wow.
Julane Lowe: Yeah?
Joe Mo: Yeah.
Joe Mo: And really brought a breath of fresh air in terms of thinking from an outsider perspective, and it's really kind of changed the way we look at things, so we're very… we, and myself in particular, are much more open to finding ways to help situations like yours, but also then reap the benefits of that partnership. So, you know, we're open to what you may find.
Joe Mo: With respect to, you know, connecting you a little bit more on the technical side, folks who could talk to you… talk that through with you. Or any other questions you have, you've got my email. Feel free to, you know, put together a list of questions.
Joe Mo: send it our way. I'm kind of… the little bit I've gathered from what you're working on, I'm kind of excited about that. I'm a big fan of what Cornell Tech is doing on Roosevelt Island, so I support that, and if we can give you a little bit of help along the way, happy to do it.
Rachel Liu: Amazing. Thank you so much. We'll look out for that email from you, Joe, to maybe connect us with some more people. The API, that can be found within New York City Open Data, or is that… Okay, perfect.
Joe Mo: We'll give you a link, too, just to be safe.
Rachel Liu: Amazing. Thank you so much.
Mujtaba Asghar: Beautiful.
Joe Mo: Best of luck. Bye.
Julane Lowe: Good luck. Good luck, guys.
Rachel Liu: Thank you.